OpenAI has just posted
that they may
have solved
the Navier-Stokes
millennium problem,
which is one
of the most famous
unsolved problems
in mathematics.
Essentially, they said
that roughly 10,000
AI agents worked
in parallel for like 88
hours and exchanged
like millions
of messages.
The final proof
was formalized in Lean,
so parts of the logical
structure can be checked
by a computer.
The model that
did most of this isn't
even publicly available,
OpenAI says it's
some internal system
significantly
more capable than GPT-6
Astra.
So technically,
Navier-Stokes is not
officially solved yet,
the proof still
has to survive scrutiny
from mathematicians
and the Clay Mathematics
Institute requires years
of outside validation.
So what exactly
is this problem?
I'm not a mathematician,
but essentially
if you start
with like a perfectly
smooth fluid in three
dimensions,
do the equations
guarantee
that it will stay smooth
forever?
Or can mathematics
essentially blow up
producing a singularity
where velocity becomes
infinite in finite time?
And so today they
kind of posted
that the answer is yes,
Navier-Stokes
can blow up.